Guide to the Archives of Industrial Society (AIS) Assorted Research Papers, 1929-2017 AIS.Research.Papers
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Archives of Industrial Society (AIS) Assorted Research Papers
1929-2017
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Archives Service Center
AIS.Research.Papers
3 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
This collection includes approximately 100 individual research papers that were produced by faculty, students and members of the larger Pittsburgh community and submitted to the Archives Service Center for inclusion in the Archives of Industrial Society (AIS) over several decades. The topics cover a wide range of subjects including immigration, ethnicity, labor, family history, municipal structure, education and politics.
Access Restrictions
All the material in this collection are available for use in the ASC Reading Room only. Since the research papers have been assembled from various sources and not necessarily donated by the original authors, not all are available to be reproduced. Any papers that can be reproduced are indicated by an asterisk (*) before the name of the author.
Acquisition Information
The research papers were collected by the Archives Service Center over many decades through a variety of acquisition methods. The History Department at the University of Pittsburgh collected student and faculty reasearch papers that were written for courses or for presentation at local history conferences and submitted to the archives. Also included in the collection are papers that were written by community members for course or seminar work and later submitted their to the archives. No grades are indicated on any paper originally submitted for course work.
Associations; Social action; Labor; Ethnic groups; Politics; Education
- Adams, John C., "Machine Politics in Action: Pittsburgh in the Early 1890's", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- *Allen, Dorothy E."A Visionary Profile: The Emergence of Blacks in Wilkinsburg (An Historical Persepective)", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Apt, Rachel.,"Economy and Ecology: Environmental Justice in Pittsburgh, 1890-1950", 2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Barnes, William H.,"Garbage and Rubbish Collection and Disposal, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania: 1910-1940", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Baraff, Ron,"Forward Into the Past: The Revitalization of the Manchester Neighborhood", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bastaja, Mark G.,"The Hardscapes and Architectural Features in the Landscape Designed by Ralph E. Griswold, Fellow of the American Academy in Rome and Fellow of the American Society of Landscape Architects" (Chatham College), 2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Becer, Allan,"An Appalling Disaster: The Allegheny Arsenal and the Great Explosion of 1862", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Becer, Allan,"Nobody Knows for Us, Croatians in a Pittsburgh Neighborhood, the Lawrenceville Experience", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- *Bendle, Jean D., [A Czechoslovakian Immigrant Story], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Blackett, R. J. M.,"'…Freedom, or the Martyr's Grave'. Black Pittsburgh's Aid to the Fugitive Slave.", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- *Brinkley, Mary Lou,"Pattern of Settlement and Residence in American Cities", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bryan, Sam,"Fifth Avenue High School: An Inner-City School as a Reflection of a Changing Neighborhood", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Burnworth, Harold F.,"A Pittsburgh Goodwill Tour to Ten Nations, Including Russia", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Cavalier, Jane,"The Effects of Public Housing on East Liberty", undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Cizmic, Ivan,"The Involvement of Yugoslav Socialists in the Socialist Party of America and the Socialist Labor Party of America 1903-1924", undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- *Coleman, Wyonna S.,"A Feeling of Security: The Iron and Coal Police—Armed Paternalism in the Coal Camps, 1926-1933", 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Coombs, C. Garn,"Law Enforcement in an Urban Setting: The Struggle for a Police System in Pittsburgh, 1802-1868", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Couvares, Francis M.,"Labor and Leisure in Pittsburgh: Some Tendencies in Late Nineteenth Century Working Class Culture", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Duncan, Clarence Barclay,"Evolution of the Government of Pittsburgh", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Feldman, Jacob S.,"The Early Migration and Settlement of Jews in Pittsburgh, 1754-1894", undated (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
- *Fesz, Judith Orzechowski,"Social History of Three Generations of Irish Women", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Forberger, Victor J.,"Labor Relations in US Steel, The Duquesne Works from 1955 to 1965", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- *Flake, Sharon G.,"Three Generational Study", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Freifeld, Alice,"The Chastened Crowd in Habsburg Hungary", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- French, John D.,"Labor Activity in Holyoke and Chicopee Massachusetts, 1933 to 1950.", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Galloway, James S.,"The Negro in Politics in Pittsburgh, 1928-1940", Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Garland, William E., Jr.,"Police Reform and Patrolman Behavior: The Pittsburgh Police Bureau; 1887-1899", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- *Gibson, Lillian,"What Jewish Writers Are Saying About Jews in America", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- *Harris, Ilene D.,"Jewish Law of Divorce", Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Helfeld,"Planning and Government in Pittsburgh: A Case Study", Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- *Iandiorio, Edward, [Study of African-American History], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Iandiorio, Edward,"3 ½ Generations", Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Kessler, Elaine,"Attitudes, Values, and Needs of a Sample of People in the Manchester Area of the North Side", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Landesman, Sarah,"The Early History of the McKeesport Jewish Community", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- *Lehrer, Penina,"Ethnic Women: A Three Generational Study", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Lloyd, Paul,"A Study of Social Control in Bethlehem Steel Company and the Westinghouse Companies, 1900-1916.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- *Lovasic, Sharon,"The Sulek Story", Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- *Lovasic, Sharon J.,"Slavic Cultures in America", Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Magdovitz, Faith Lynn,"A Comparison of the Changing Functions of Two Jewish Community Centers as Exemplified by the Jewish Community Center in Cincinnati, Ohio, and the Anna B. Heldman Center in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, (Formerly the Irene Kauffman Center).", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- *Majewski, Tom,"Life in the United States", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- *Majewski, Tom,"Land of Equality???", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- *Majhan, Cabrina,"A Three Generational Study of Croatian Women in America", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- *Matta, Vincent A.,"Topic: The American Jew", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Mazerov, Esther B.,"The History of the Petroleum Industry in Pittsburgh, Medicine, Refineries, Monopolies, 1794-1911", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- McClain, Raymond,"The Immigrant Years: Irene Kaufmann Settlement, 1895-1915",McClain, Raymond,"The Immigrant Years: Irene Kaufmann Settlement, 1895-1915", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- McKay, John P.,"John Cockerill in Southern Russia, 1885-1905; A Study of Aggressive Foreign Entrepreneurship", Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
- McShea, Mary & Bob Connolly,"Pete Flaherty, Politician", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- *Mervosh, Nick Jr.,"Mrvos, Three Generations", Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Miller, Cheryl Lynn,"Loyalties of German- Americans in Pittsburgh During World War I.", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Miller, Roger G.,"Archival Sources for a Study of United States Army Personnel, 1869-1870", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Misko, Louise,"Family History", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Moore, Branden,"Where the Evidence Led", 2009 (Box 2, Folder 5a)
- Morano, Eloise Danniels, "Historic Hartwood Acres: Reclaiming Pittsburgh's Last Country Place Era Landscape," (Chatham College), 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5b)
- Murcko, Anita C.,"My Progenitors: An Un*Family Tree", Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- *Oresick, Peter M.,"An Early Family History with Historical Perspectives", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- *Oresick, Peter,"A Family History of Stephanie Lane from Oresick", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Pailthrop, Michelle,"The German-Jewish Elite of Pittsburgh: Its Beginnings and Background", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Plank, Kathryn M.,"The Steel Novel: A View of Industrial Pittsburgh", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- *Rawa, Charles Anthony,"An Overall View of Polish Immigration and Lifestyle from Then to Now", Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- *Rocco, Emma Scogan,"The Italian Heritage in Monaco, Pennsylvania (Beaver County)", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- *Rocco, Emma S.,"Ethnicity Patterns, Syrian, Sarah George Sam", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Rosen, Philip,"Thirty Years at Kingsley House", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- *Rosenthal, Debra "Escaped?", Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Ruoff, Fred,"History of the First United Evangelical Protestant Church" [English translation of German text, published in 1882] (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Sacks, Aaron & Maurice B. Greenbaum,"An Approach to Group Work with New Americans (A Description of a Club Group at the Young Men and Women's Hebrew Association of Pittsburgh, 1949-1950)", Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- *Sauers, Barbara,"My Family History", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Schubert, Jane G.,"A Man and His City", 1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- *Scott, Denise,"The Yiddish Theater in America", Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- *Seamon, Mary E.R.,"My Slovak Heritage", Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Selavan, Ida Cohen,"Adolph Edlis: A Hungarian Jew in Pittsburgh Politics" (Tenth Annual Conference on Ethnic and Minority Studies), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- *Sell, Nannette,"Syrian-American Women and their Development", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- *Shirey, Sandra S.,"Anti-Semitism in America, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- *Skirble, Debra Lynn,"Jewish Home & Hospital for Aged at Pittsburgh", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Smith, Hal,"The Show Trials of the Accused "Molly Mcguires" Patrick Hester, Peter McHugh, and Patrick Tully", Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Smith, Roland M.,"The Politics of Flood Control on the Allegheny and Monongahela Rivers at Pittsburgh, 1908-1936", 1971 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Smith, Roland M.,"The Politics of Pittsburgh Flood Control, 1908-1936", Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Smith, Roland M.,"The Politics of Pittsburgh Flood Control, 1936-1960", Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Soens, Ted C. & Jack L. Hiller & Jarrell McCrackenTitle: "Morningside: An Urban Village", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Studnicki, Anthony,"Cardinal Karol Wojtyla's First Visit to the United States", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Tarr, Joel A.,"Growth, Stability, and Decline in an Urban Area: One Hundred Years of Hazelwood", Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Taylor, Donald L.,"The Woods Run Settlement, 1895-1932", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Teneholz, Beverly,"Three Generations of Ethnic Women", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- *Verk, Rita,"Intermarriage: A Jewish Problem", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Walsh, Victor A.,"Class, Culture, and Nationalism: The Irish Catholics of Pittsburgh, 1870-1883", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- *Wherthey, John P.,"Ann Bedzyk & Frank Lesak", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- *Wherthey, John P.,"My Grandmother, Mary (Babjack) Fader, 1889-1964", Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
- *Williamson, Jeffry J.,"The History of the Horner Family", 1980 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- *Wilson, Bonnie G.,"A Three Generational Study", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- *Wilson, Bonnie G.,"A Memorial to the Immigrant, the Nationality Rooms with Specific Emphasis on the Irish Room at the University of Pittsburgh", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Wilson, Cathy A.,"The Western Pennsylvania Hospital Site", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- *Wilson, Robert E.,"1968 Civil Rights Act Rights at Last?", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- *Wilson, Robert E.,"Christmas: Past and Present, A Study of the Wilson Family Traditions", Undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Wood, Diana M.,"An Analysis of the Pittsburgh Elementary School Boards, 1900-1906: Leadership and Values", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- *Wooler, Elizabeth L.,"A Three Generational Study of Ethnic Greek Women", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Wudarczyk, James,"A History of the Heppenstall Company", Undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
- *Yarkosky, Linda,"My Slovene Heritage in America, Slavic Culture in America", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Zoidis, Marilyn,"A Class of Their Own: Pittsburgh's College Women in the Early Twentieth Century", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Paterson, Thomas G., "Barbara Paterson (1871-1933) and her Hosie Family in Scotland, the United States, and Austrialia", 2017 (Box 2, Folder 50)